[Music]
hey welcome back today is day two the
tinkerer can't what we're going to be
working on today is building on the
skills that we got yesterday so we're
gonna continue to work with variables to
get better with tinker and today we're
gonna do some things with drawing it's
kind of one of the skills that we worry
about now whenever I say hey the skill
for today is drawing people are like hey
that's not coding but it is right so
coding creating apps creating projects
there's a lot of design emerges really
well with art and music and so today one
of the main things we're doing is
working our drawing we're stuck in the
right code too so here's the game that
we're gonna make so we're gonna make a
game it's called Treasure Island you can
kinda love whatever you want but the
idea of Treasure Island is that your
boat chases your mouse and you're trying
to successfully get to the treasure
if you succeed it'll say you win but
then it'll say let's go faster right and
then what we're doing is if you watch
the variable in the corner see where it
says speed 20 up there watch what
happens if I went again it says speed 40
and so our speed which is our variable I
gets fast for each time and then if you
do hit an island it'll say you wrecked
your ship and that will be the game over
and what we're gonna do is we're gonna
make this together you wrecked your ship
and then you're challenged for today if
you like a challenge is to build the
same concept so you're gonna build
another game which also has this like
your actor follows your ship here it is
the ship again here he's trying to get
home so you made at home and then of
course it says let's go faster so I
think that's the that's the idea and
then if you wreck it does that so that's
what we're trying to build today we're
gonna work on drawing variables and
doing more code so go ahead and go to
your projects and click on create new
project and of course what we want is we
want a blank block coding project so I
always click on block coding and go down
here now if you were to click blank
project up here I think it's the exact
same as blank block coding project but
I'm gonna go ahead and say blank block
coding
project I just because that is
definitely what we're making so the
first thing we want to do we've kind of
got ourselves set up here we if you
remember don't need a monster in this
one so the first thing I'm gonna do is
I'm going to delete my monster I saw I'm
gonna click on these little three dots
over here and say delete and it'll say
you sure you want to delete actor
because he is an actor and his name is
actor so I'm going to delete him and
then what I want to do instead is I want
to have a pirate ship so I'm going to
click on add actor whenever you're
adding an actor you could just draw the
actor if you wanted you could do these
special character builders like our
monster had these special features but
normally what we do is we just go to the
media library so go ahead and click on
media library and then what we're doing
is we're looking for the pirate ship is
the one that I'm after you could use a
different one but make sure it's some
type of like vessel that moves right so
what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna look for
ship in the search bar and I'm gonna see
what comes up so you can pick a
different thing if you'd like you could
use an alien ship in the water or a
spaceship if you'd like but I think that
one of these ships like the pirate ship
this pirate ship the Viking boat or the
trading ship are gonna fit best
thematically from my game so I'm gonna
go ahead and just click on pirate ship
so what that does is that adds an actor
to your to your game right so we've got
an actor over here his name is pirate
ship I think that's a fine name no no
need to change that name and he got
plopped onto our stage now to be honest
he came onto our stage quite big if you
remember mine compared to my stage the
pirate ship was actually very small that
way I could kind of like make an
intricate you know island may use for
him to get through so I'm gonna take my
pirate ship and I'm gonna make him quite
a bit smaller and then I'm gonna go
ahead and just kind of move him up to a
corner
so games like this you could really do
in about any order you could write code
for the pirate-ship first you could draw
your background first it really doesn't
matter I think what I'm going to do is
I'm going to write just a little bit of
code because I've already kind of
started my pirate ship and then after
that I'm gonna go do some drawing and
drawing it's going to be kind of the
interesting things that really bring
this together so what I'm going to do is
I'm going to click on my pirate ship
here you can see that I'm adding code
for the pirate ship because I've got his
little icon and I'm just gonna go and
write a little code for him typically in
games you have an on start and so on
start is code that runs whenever you
want to restart this game and what I'm
gonna choose to do here is I'm gonna be
a little like controlling I'm gonna add
a go to block just to make sure my
pirates dip starts in the correct spot
now this go to block isn't strictly
necessary because obviously he's gonna
start somewhere and I don't need it but
I want to make sure he starts in the
upper left corner here for me if you
want to use a different corner that's
that's totally fine now I will say that
right now my pirate ship if I kind of
hover my mouse over him he's sitting at
a certain location so I've got to kind
of keep my mouse there so you can see it
but see those numbers that are down here
my pirate ship right now is at the
location x equals negative 641 y equals
305 so what I'm going to do is I'm going
to get a sheet of paper so pause the
video and go get a sheet of paper it's
nice to have a sheet of paper so you can
write down some numbers right I so I'm
gonna get a sheet of paper and I'm gonna
write those numbers down on the sheet of
paper so for me it's negative 641 Y 305
so now I've got that written down so now
if I move my cursor and they go away it
doesn't matter and I want to put them
into my code so I typed negative 614 and
then you can actually hit tab if you
want 305 and so whatever numbers you
found so you put your cursor up on the
ship and you found
numbers if I do it again they're
slightly different right you wrote them
on your sheet of paper we're gonna be
using the sheet of paper quite a bit
today and then you moved your mouse and
you type them in and the reason we wrote
them down is because we have to move our
mouse to go type of mam and then we
can't see them anymore
if you want to just memorize two numbers
I'm sure you could but a sheet of paper
is gonna be handy a lot today so now
even if our pirate ship was somewhere
different if I start the game he's gonna
go to that spot so it's a guaranteed way
that he'll start in that spot I'm gonna
just kind of move him up in that area
anyway the next thing I want to do is I
want my pirate ship to run code forever
and ever where he follows the mouse now
if you have a really good memory you
might be able to do this based on what
we did last time but of course I'm gonna
do it with you so the first thing I want
to do is I want to drag out a forever
chunk I went through this a little
faster I didn't say but it's in the
control area and then the forever trunk
the goal of these apps is that as you do
more and more you start to get more and
more comfortable and you can actually
like start to do some things you know
more on your own as you get better and
then I want him to point towards the
mouse pointer and then go ten steps so
point towards is a type of motion so I'm
going to go into the motion area and
then in the motion area I'm gonna look
for point towards mouse pointer now the
one people always grab is this one go to
mouse pointer that is not point towards
mouse pointer so I'm gonna just kind of
put that on there just so you can see it
but the command I want is point towards
mouse pointer and the difference is
point towards doesn't move him he just
he just kind of aims it back right that
way he'll take some number of steps
based on the speed and not just warp
there instantly
so go-to is bad I'm gonna get rid of
that the next thing I want to do is I
want to move ten steps so move ten steps
is the very first of the move commands
and I'm gonna say move ten pixels
and one thing that you do whenever
you're coding is you stop and you try it
right so we have we have plenty of code
here to try it so let's go ahead and run
our code and we'll see if he follows her
mouse ah this was a good test because I
forgot something important so as I move
it he basically just stays with my mouse
no matter what I have a bug in my code I
didn't do it on purpose it just just I
forgot to have something right and the
thing I forgot to add is speed is a
function of how far you move and how
long you take to do it and right now
he's moving 10 pixels but there's no
time delay right so his speed is
infinitely fast so I needed a time delay
I just forgot I've been using scratch
too much Oh scratch you don't need it
so I need a small time delay so go to
control inside control add a weight so
you have to like scroll down until you
find it it was actually really near the
bottom so if you go all the way to the
bottom you'll find this wait one second
and you can drop it in to the bottom of
your code now one second is too slow
right if I if I run this now he's gonna
just be crawling right so every one
second it moves ten pixels I don't know
about you but I think that's way too
slow so let's make the time be smaller a
number that I use a lot is 0.05 that's
five hundredths of a second and so
basically that makes your game be it
what's called twenty frames per second
I'm not worried about the frames per
second math but he's going to move ten
pixels every five hundredth of a second
and now this is a more reasonable speed
right so now he's moving and everything
is going fine if he gets to the mouse
pointer he does kind of freak out there
are ways that we could fix that but I'm
not worried about I'm gonna call that a
feature and the next thing I want to do
is I want to reinforce
we've done with variables so instead of
moving ten pixels I want to make a
variable so the variable that we're
going to make is called speed so to make
a variable we've done this before but
obviously we need to practice things
it's in the variables area inside the
variables area near the top I was kind
of scrolled down there I want to create
a variable now whenever you create a
variable it's that orange button that I
clicked on whenever you create a
variable and I ask you a couple
questions the questions that I ask you
is to ask you what do you want to name
your variable this variable is going to
be for the speed and then there's this
question of do I want it for all actors
or do I want to for just this actor last
time if you remember we said all actors
and that was because it controlled the
speed of the monster I guess it was food
then but the cupcakes changed it so both
people used it now it's just gonna be
the shit so you can actually just say
for this actor only which was the
default for me so now I go ahead and
click on create now at this point I have
a variable it sits in my computer it's
there but I can't see the value all I
like to do is I'm gonna add a text
watcher if you remember how to add a
text watcher you click on the variable
over here I think the text Watchers are
kind of sneaky because it doesn't show
you the button until you click on it
right so it's kind of like hidden until
you click on it and then we click on add
watcher so that adds a small watcher
onto my screen now if you remember last
time there was a bug that we had to
change in the code that's because it was
a global that bug won't exists this time
so we can actually just hit play and we
should see the value of speed which I
forgot to set again all right every time
I seem to forget this at the set the
speed so last time just to share we had
to like change something in here I don't
think that's an
sorry this time but we do still need to
set the speed making lots of good errors
today that's just how it goes so I'm
going to as the first thing in my code
I'm going to grab this set and I'm going
to drop it right after on start I did
that kind of fast I'm just going to kind
of show it one more time
so inside variables I do set and I drop
it into my code right there that is one
nice thing about block languages you can
always just look at my finished product
and right now it doesn't know what
variable to set so I'm going to click on
the drop down and say speed we have
alright that's the hold on got got a
question so I'm gonna pause here I've
got my campers with me again today I
didn't even say that all right so what's
your question
oh yeah so I've got got code like this
so the problem is and you did a great
job of following along is that I did
something quickly that I didn't mention
to you right now you're changing the
code for the speed watcher but I'm
changing the code for my hero so this is
currently in the wrong spot so Boeing
you're gonna have to take take something
out so to take something out click on
the little handle on the far right and
trash that and now switch over to the
sleepy dragon and now grab a set for the
sleepy dragon and put it up here now bow
in your code and my code I look to be a
lot better so that makes sense bone
great job you can do good alright
alright so let's keep going
so speed my goal with speed is that I'm
gonna start speed at a low number you
could start it at 10 or you could start
it at 15 somewhere in that ballpark just
depending on what you feel is best and
then what we're gonna do oh I'm gonna do
my little test first so I set it to 10
and what I want to do is I want to see
if
texe watchers working so I'm just gonna
run it really quick just to see if my
text lectures working and it is workin
right so there was no no bug today so
what should happen is you should see
your variable up on your stage by the
way if you ever want your stage to be
bigger you can just click on this little
tab at the top and you can just see the
stage very quickly there now we've made
a variable we can see the value of the
variable but we're not using it anywhere
and we're not changing it anywhere we're
gonna change it later well let's go
ahead and use it for now so take speed
so this is your speed variable drag
speed into move speed pixels and so now
what's gonna happen is your ship is
going to move based on that variable I
so just to kind of test it let's say you
put your speed at 50 so the speed of 50
should be quite a bit faster and you hit
play then you're kind of zipping around
with the speed of 50 and of course if
your speed was slower let's say I tried
to that would make my ship move quite a
bit slower so you can see that this
variable is being used but right now
it's not changing and then when you're
done with that test put it back to it in
between value now if you did that great
it's fun like CJ code changes but you
could also just watch mine and Bend just
fine so I think our ship is actually
doing pretty well I think the biggest
problem that we have now is that our
ship is sailing in complete whiteness
right it's not a very good island so I'm
gonna go ahead and save it so to save it
right here it says untitled at the top
I'm gonna save it as Treasure Island you
can save it as anything you want after I
do that I'm going to click on the Save
button you certainly don't need to add a
description and you will publish it
later but for now I'm just going to
click Save right so this is the week 1
day 2
demo and adults feel free to do some of
the typing with them unless you want
that to be a skill that people are
learning alright so I'm ready to add a
stage now last time when we added a
backdrop for the stage we just used an
image so I put in a kitchen and it was
just like boom there this time if you
kind of like Lance up my finished
product this time what's going to happen
is we're going to draw so we're gonna
have to fill in the water with a blue
color and we're gonna have to draw
different islands now one thing to think
about as you draw your islands is think
about the size of your ship now you have
to make a game to where your ship can
get through your obstacles where it's
possible but it's also you know
potentially kind of fun and challenging
right so don't make it too easy
and don't make it too hard and this is
where the creativity aspect comes in I
also like to add little challenges of
mine like where somebody like things
they might be able to shoot it through
the middle I can't believe I just did
that I maybe I make it through the
middle like 1 in 10 times right and then
you know it's it's a fun challenging
game so that's kind of the idea so let's
go start brawling so click on the stage
you'll notice that the stage has no code
and there's no backdrop yet so the only
thing if you click on the stage is this
gear so go and click on this little gear
and what we want to do is and it says
hey the stage can't up costume sounds
and advanced things we want costumes and
so we want to click on add background so
go and click on add backgrounds ok now
this screen we saw last time this is
actually trying to encourage you to
select a different background but we
want to do this time is we want to draw
so up here at the top there's a little
paintbrush and so this is where we're
gonna draw image so go and click on
drawl image and for some reason you have
to click it again tip to come draw image
again maybe if we came back in here I
would see something different so now we
are to the heart of today so this is the
drawing interface so the first thing
we're going to do is we're going to draw
some together
to learn and then we're going to delete
it and then we'll come back for the real
thing so this we're just we're just kind
of learning so let's kind of learn more
about what this setup is so there's
different like drawing tools over all
the left and then there's different
colors on the bottom so for this example
I don't care what color you pick but
pick some fun color that you'd like to
just kind of test with does not have to
be related to the ship we're going to
delete this here in a little bit and
what we're going to do is we're gonna
select the pencil so the pencil is one
of your main drawing tools with the
pencil you can change how big it is
right so go ahead and with the pencil I
just kind of draw a little bit and you
can kind of see how drawing with the
pencil works now if somebody is is a
great artist maybe they could draw you
know something fun I'm a lousy artist
right so my art with a pencil would be
not very good but I do really like that
tinker and scratch both really encourage
and allow creativity and drawing there
was a recent post on tinker where she
draws a dog and like she's just amazing
so look up virtual pet some time on
thinker and you'll see how good she is
at drawing things right
other skills that we want to learn so
that's the pencil there's also the brush
the brush is for adding like artistic
effects so you notice that the brush is
similar to the pencil and that you can
change size but the brush has this like
opacity meter so this is where you can
add like you know really elaborate
shadings to your drawing and things like
that so we don't need the brush today
but I wanted to point out the brush the
eraser tool is fairly self-explanatory
it erases right so you can erase things
the fill the Paint Bucket this one's
interesting this one will let you fill
in any closed shape so let's say that I
clicked on my Paint Bucket I clicked on
this yellow and then I click inside my
circle and you'll notice that it fills
it all in now the thing you have to be
careful about with fill
is that it does have to be like a closed
shape so for example let's say that I
put my mouse right here and I click
right here
but what anything's going to happen if I
click right here with yellow yeah it's
just gonna do the whole entire screen so
if I click there it just does the whole
entire screen yellow and that's because
phil has to be a closed shape and you'll
notice that this one is it's very much
open so when we're drawing Islands today
I just kind of wanted to to reinforce
this if you draw an island like this
it's gonna work perfectly if you draw an
island like that it's gonna work very
badly right so if I fill that one in
oops I need to go to my my fill I fill
this one then it works great if I fill
this Island in it works very badly so
just kind of be aware that that's how
the fill tool works the stamp tool is
fun it's just for adding a little like
decorations to your to your thing
usually when you stamp something it's
not for functionality it's just for fun
right and so if you ever want to
decorate your your art you can do some
stamps you can go crazy with these
things right these other tools we're not
going to use as much today but I thought
I'd point them out so there's a line
tool do notice the line also has this
thing called opacity so I'm just going
to kind of ensure that there's squares
there's there's all kinds of things you
can do right the other thing is text
text is fun because you can decide what
font you want to use so if I wanted to
say David Fisher I can do it in a cool
flat now I'm gonna point out something
tricky cuz you guys are good let's let's
say what's what's tricky about the
drawing tool well one thing that's
tricky is I just typed this and if I
just typed it and I drag it I can move
it to say right there now as soon as I
click off on it
what's happened is I've clicked off on
it and it's it's it's called a blip
that's what it is and it's it's been
painted on to the background I can no
longer just grab it at this point right
so that's how tinker works
if I just kind of do another example
here so this is a test whenever I make
it I can kind of move it around but as
soon as I let go of it it's done
it sits on there right so it got pasted
in and that same thing is true for four
rectangles and you know I could I can
grab it I can actually resize it but as
soon as I let go of it as soon as I
click somewhere else
it's pasted onto the screen it's called
bitmap mode if you're used to scratch
and you've used its vector mode this
does behave differently now what's
worrying about one other thing I've been
making this game I've been making this
backdrop and I happen to know that what
I'm looking at on the screen is actually
not the whole stage and the reason I
know that it's because see these bars on
the side saying they don't fill the
whole thing zoom out for me so it turns
out that my stage was actually bigger
than what I was looking at right and
that's just something you have to be
careful of so you have to be careful if
you're drawing so like I've done this
mistake a couple times but I start
drawing and like I fill up the whole
thing and then I realized later that I
was actually waves good cool so that is
a beautiful backdrop I'm pretty proud of
it but I want to start fresh all right
so that is your opportunity to go nuts
if you need another second draw draw
like crazy but now what we're gonna do
is we're gonna work together to build
something specific so your dots on this
sheet as much as you want but on the
next one let's try to actually achieve a
mission right so I clicked on add a
costume it gives me a nice blank slate
just because I feel like it it's called
blank one but I'm gonna change the name
to be islands that is not necessary I
just just don't like doing it the next
thing I want to do is I want to change
my zoom level to try to like make sure
I'm seeing everything right so if I
change my zoom level to where I'm seeing
everything I feel like seeing everything
so now we're trying to do something
specific so we're trying to make an
ocean so pick your favorite color of
blue so my favorite color of blue is I
could pick just this one down here at
the bottom if you don't like that shade
of blue there's this color picker down
here I don't know if you've seen this
yet but for this color picker I can pick
any shade of blue that I would like and
then once you've got the color you want
you can hit the X so now you've got the
world's best shade of blue and then you
want to go to the paint bucket and you
want to click anywhere and what that
should do is actually turn your whole
world blue right so now you have a blue
world now what we're going to do is
we're going to start drawing the outline
of Islands
so to draw the outline of Islands we're
going to use the most common tool the
pencil tool the size can be either 14 or
20 something near the top is fine by the
way you can use this slider and you can
get other values too I'm just gonna go
ahead and draw with 20 that'll be fine
and now I need to pick the color for my
islands now for the coding reasons your
islands all have to be the same color
because what the ship is doing is it
saying hey if I touch this color that I
that I'm doing right so let's pick the
color for your islands I'm gonna go with
kind of like some type of green color
but if you want to use a different color
that's fine let's say you like purple
Islands that's no big deal right if you
wanted to you could also like pick a
very specific color inside the color
picker that'd be just fine
I maybe I'll go with kind of like a dark
green island and what I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna draw my islands so here's
where your your creativity comes in I'm
gonna choose to have kind of like one
big island and then a couple other small
more islands so you can see with the way
I'm gonna strategize my game I'm gonna
make it to where you could if your risky
shoot through the short cut but then
it's easier if you go a lot around the
long way so
not gonna you know give you an unlimited
amount of time to do this you're
probably gonna have to pause the video
but you can draw shapes for each of this
right kids love to draw and if your
first pass goes weld and super I hope it
goes badly you know you can always do it
again so I'm gonna draw all some shapes
just to kind of like make my game tricky
and what I'm trying to keep in mind is
is there some way my ship can like get
through to the other side and I think
that I've kind of done that with my
shapes once you've got a couple shapes
it's time to fill them in to fill a menu
go to your paint bucket and you fill in
your very shapes and you can zoom in to
try to like hit them better if you want
or whatever you need now you'll notice
that for me whenever I make a circle
like this and then fill it in I get kind
of like this little outline if that
outline bugs yeah that's fine you can
come back through with your pencil and
you can get rid of that outline right so
if you are not an OCD person feel free
just to leave it because it doesn't
affect anything badly it's just that
it's there so go ahead and pause the
video and get your islands just right
hey my crew was a drawing and they they
occasionally wanted to like erase
something and turn it back to blue and a
skill that they used a lot was this
eyedropper tool so if they ever needed
to draw in blue again you say eyedropper
and blue and then that lets you kind of
have an opportunity to kind of like draw
in your blue so like I could dido loop
this out a little bit more or if they
wanted to draw more on their island
color they could use the eyedropper
click there island color and then they
could draw a little bit more than color
so that was a good skill for them and
the next thing we want to do is we want
to put another color on here which is
our victory color and so this is like
our goal or target that we're trying to
get to and so let's go ahead and draw
I'll just go and use the pencil again I
use a big pencil but pick a new color
for your career victory so this is kind
of like your your gold right and so
somewhere I just kind of like put a
little patch that is your goal so if the
ship gets to here then you're gonna win
now interestingly I picked a very
different color I just so you could see
it quite vividly but it couldn't be
similar in color just so long as it's
it's different a little bit right so
that's my goal now if you would like to
decorate you can with one caveat you
cannot use either of those two colors so
if you start like making stamps and
things if there are completely different
colors you can do that I'm not going to
do a lot of decoration but I would like
to add some text to my Big Island and
the text that I'm gonna add is I'm gonna
add white text so I click on color so
I'm gonna click on white color here and
I'm gonna click on text and I'm gonna
pick the font that I think is best now I
like Pacifico right so I use Pacifica a
lot and you can change what size your
letters are gonna come out I'm gonna I'm
gonna pick about a 60 or so and now I'm
going to click somewhere to type now you
can type anywhere because you can still
move it after you finish typing but you
only get to move it like one time and
then as soon as you let go
it's it stuck on there just for giggles
I will make a mistake right so I'm gonna
click up here I'm gonna say you know
Dave Fisher's islands and so I want this
to be moved into here right now if I did
mess up let's say I put it up here and
then I let go of it I'd stuck there
right by the way it jumped a little bit
another trick that you really should
know about is the undo button right so
you click on the undo button and that
will make your life a lot easier so I
should have told you about that that
button a long time ago so if you want to
add text or something you can so there
I'm going to add Dave Fisher
Islands and then once you're happy with
that we can click on save and we can go
back to the other one so I've got who
actually before we go back let's do one
more thing let's write down some stuff
onto our sheet of paper so our code
needs to know what colors were used so
we're gonna need that in our code so
what I want to do is I want to know
exactly what shade of green is that
exactly what shade of pink is that so
here's what I'm gonna do to figure that
out I'm gonna click on the eyedropper so
follow along with me even if you're
doing something different click on the
eyedropper click on you're your death
color so click on one of your islands
and then click on this light color
selector I know it's like 18 steps right
and then click on hex so the number you
need the number you need is this hex
color right here so on your sheet of
paper write down your hex color don't
worry you'll see the whole process again
when I do it for for the next one I also
hate the font that they used because
there are some numbers and some letters
just so you know how it works
the letters if it's a letter is going to
be a through F and the numbers are 4 0
through 9 so mine here is 6 5 8 0 3 B so
there's an 8 and a B in there I know
that's super annoying so hold on let's
go through that process again so you
click on the eyedropper you click on the
thing that you want to discover then you
click on the color chooser and then you
click on hex by the way scratch makes
this way easier but let's not think it
works so now I'm going to write down the
color of my my victory all that when I
maybe could have memorized kind of looks
like the word food except for those O's
or zeros yeah O's and zeros are never a
question you know that it's a number you
know that it's a zero because the
letters can only be a through F right so
this one is FF 0 0 D 5 so yeah it's like
a
four-step process so you click on color
chooser I'm sorry I dropper then the
color chooser and then hax and that's
the number that your codes going to need
so I've written down both of mine and
then I'm gonna put a little annotation
next to them for which one is green and
which one is pink for me right by the
way if you happen to really like know
about colors and light colors and what a
lot about hexadecimals this number is
meaningful but that's not now or up to
today cool so once you've got your
colors written down you're done with the
drawing part of today that's the main
part of today and you can go back to
your game now when I click back
it looks like I've still got the two two
drawings that are made in here you can
see I'm kind of switching in the
backdrop I want the one that's the
islands right so make sure that you've
got the island set up now if you're
having problems like getting your Island
one set up you could always add code to
like explicitly set it so you could say
like switch background - but mine looks
like it's working fine so I'm not gonna
add any code alright let's finish this
game so let's go to our pirate ship so
right now if you play your game you can
sail right through your islands it
doesn't really matter right so that's
just how this game works how you can say
all right over here and touch your
treasure but nothing happens there
either the reason I'm doing this is
because this is a way to test I did you
did you do a good job with your game
right like can you go through your
various obstacles to be honest if
anything mine's almost too easy right so
I can fit right through there um so you
can tweak things like that to your
heart's content but I'm not gonna make
time to do now I'm gonna call mine good
enough so that we can all move forward
right so now let's let's have the pirate
ship check am i touching the islands and
if so I lose right or am i touching the
goal um and if so I win so a check is an
if statement so an if statement is in
control and so we're going to add an if
statement for a my touching
the island and then because we know that
this code is coming I'm gonna go ahead
and add another if statement that's
gonna be like am i touching victory
right so it's either have I died or have
I won and if neither of those things are
happened then we just keep playing right
so I drug over the if it says false then
but if something then do this all right
so we want to put into these condition
statements so if this condition then do
this am i touching a certain color and
so the one that says touching color and
sensing is right here it's the fourth
one down so drop one of these in here
and then drop one of these in there now
we've got two colors we've got one color
which is it's death and the other color
which is victory what I'm going to do is
I'm going to type into this top one my
my death color right so you type in your
color and I'll type in mine and it's
going to be some combination of numbers
and letters now the nice thing is is
when you finish you should get feedback
that you did good because it should
change to be the color that matches the
stage so I'm going to do that for my
other one as well make sure you leave
that little hatch over there right so FF
so don't worry about my colors you worry
about your colors right so there I
should have typed in both of my colors
that I'm done with my sheet of paper now
right so now in my code I'm checking did
I lose
did I win and then I'm gonna do stuff in
those two situations so if you touch the
island then you've just died and so what
we want to do is we want to say
something along those lines so I like
speech bubbles again there's these
speech bubbles that are really
intimidating they have lots of features
then there's a really simple ones I
would like to use a simple one that
would be great but I need features right
so I'm going to pick the very top speech
bubble so right now it says say hello
and then for two seconds
so instead of saying hello this is where
they've just wrecked their ship right so
I'm gonna say you rekt yo ship so you
can say whatever you'd like to say so
once you get your type you might have to
pause the video but once you get your
type you can then pick the style so the
style by default is a bottom message or
bottom message like takes over this
whole bottom bar I think I would rather
it it felt like the ship was saying it
and so I'm gonna put it on a rectangular
like speech bubble but if you like the
bottom well that's fine but I'm gonna go
with the rectangular speech bubble and
in a speech bubble I happen to know the
18 is really small so I'm gonna bump it
up to 48 so I'm just gonna say you
wrecked your ship and then I'll tell
what I'll go ahead and play it right now
just so you can see a problem that's
gonna come up if you wrecked your ship
it's gonna say you wrecked your ship and
then the game is gonna keep playing and
it's gonna say that every two seconds as
you like continue to wreck your ship now
what I would rather do is I would rather
just have the game stopped so maybe you
remember how to make the game stop so to
make the game just stop that's over in
control and the very very very bottom
command in the control is stop now again
stop all is a dangerous command and you
want to put it in just the right spot so
you'll notice it's in this advanced area
because if you put it in the wrong spot
it was very badly right and so it should
be fine because I've got it inside of my
if statement so I'm going to only stop
all if I say you wrecked your ship and
then stop all if you put it anywhere
else it's kind of just be a disaster
right so that's losing and you could
test that if you wanted so now if you
hit the island it says you wrecked your
ship for two seconds maybe I'll bump it
up a little bit maybe I'll say it for
loops
it's not their own place to bump it up
maybe I'll bump it up done five seconds
or something that's loss right let's do
win so when you win we're gonna start
off by doing the same thing we're going
to start off by saying a message so
we're gonna say well I could really put
it down in there so we're gonna say
instead of hello I'm gonna say you win
and I choose to make it seem like the
ship is saying it so I'm gonna have it
say with a rectangular speech bubble and
the font size of 18 for a regular speech
bubble is too small I'm gonna go with 48
again now this is a bit harder to test
in your game so really the only good way
to to test it is to either actually win
your game or come up with a clever way
to cheat right now a clever way to cheat
would be to change that X&Y so there it
says you win right to change that X&Y
that you start it out and then you could
cheat and you can get to your victory
much faster but it looks like mine is
working fine interestingly enough the
game doesn't stop so when you win you
just keep winning and tell eventually
you hit the island behind it right so
you win now we're not gonna stop if you
remember what the other game did when
you win it doubles your speed and then
you say let's play again right so here's
what we want to do we want to put the
ship back to the starting spot we want
to say let's go faster and then we want
to modify our variable so those that's
our goal let's go ahead and start doing
some of those things so what I want to
do is I want to go back to the starting
spot now I've got those numbers written
down and I could type a line of code
that's exactly like this but we can
actually do one better we can copy this
line of code down below so click on the
little black handle that's on the right
side of this and I want to copy
line of code so I'm going to hit
control-c I don't copy it and then
control V and it's command C and command
V if you're on Mac so now I've got a
duplicate of that line and now this line
I want to put down near the bottom right
so I'm going to say you win and they're
gonna enjoy their victory for two
seconds then I'm gonna snap them back to
the beginning and I'm gonna say let's go
faster let's go faster now this one just
to show it I had made as a bottom
message box in my example and what the
heck aw I'll just leave it as a bottom
message box or you can change it to
speech bubble that doesn't matter right
now when it's a bottom message box a
font size of 18 is actually fine so I'm
gonna just leave the defaults so the
only thing I did is I changed the text
and then I left it as a bottom message
box just so you can see it and I left
the font so that's wide now our code
right now does some of the things we
want it resets the ship to the start it
says let's go faster but it doesn't
actually go faster yet um
bow and how would we go faster do you
have any ideas for how how do you go
faster in this game you have any ideas
he gives you have any ideas for how we
go faster
sissie oh yeah set we could change speed
right so let's go into variable sissy so
what you're gonna say so we're gonna
change speed now there's a couple ways
to modify speed we we can use change
that would be one way to do it we could
change it by like 10 or something like
that if you wanted to do that you could
but I'm going to show you something
different so last time we showed you
change this time we're gonna set it in
an interesting way so go ahead and grab
a set and what we're going to do is
we're gonna set speed and what we want
to do is we want to set it to double
what it was before so speed is equal to
whatever speed was before times two now
you may notice that in variables there's
no like multiplication symbol in here
that's because multiplication and things
like that are over in the operators area
and what I want to do is I want to find
the operator for multiplication it's the
third one down
it's that itty-bitty star I know it's
hard to see and what we're gonna do is
we're going to set speed to the result
of some multiplication problem now zero
times zero is not a very good
multiplication problem instead what I
want to do is I want to set it to
whatever the speed was before so that's
over in variables so I drag a speed over
and put it right here speed times two so
you can read this line of code and it's
readable set speed to speed times two so
every time your speed is going to double
so folks I think we might have a
finished game here so we are ready to
try this we can lose and we can win and
we're ready to give this thing a go so
let's go ahead and try our game so I'm
gonna try an intentional loss first it
says you wrecked your ship and then the
game just ends right so nothing nothing
else happens and now I'm gonna try to
win one right so to win mine I've kind
of got two paths I've got the shortcut
path so there's a shortcut happen
remember is my speed is currently 10 and
then it says let's go faster and so now
I'm going I'm at 20 now the reason we're
doubling is because eventually it's
going to get too hard no matter how good
you are right
so my 20 is now at 40 and it doesn't
kind of start to freak out as it goes
like super fast right I'm gonna try 80 I
can do this do this you know now 160 is
hopeless right yeah
because it just goes crazy and so I
managed to make it up to 160 which is
pretty good right alright so you can
charge your adult and see if they can do
better than you so we're done with the
coding so now that I'm done with the
coding I'm gonna click on this little
down arrow and I'm gonna say publish to
community and publish to community -
ready to go now yours may not be ready
to go you may have a lot of people do
this you may have discovered that your
island was impossible to solve or he may
have discovered it was too too easy to
solve and your job is to make it fun
right
lipstick slick on the back here I didn't
mean to do that your job is to make it
fun so you're gonna have to tweak your
island so you should understand the
concepts now shooter got to tweak your
island maybe resize your ship all kinds
of things that you can do so that's the
goal now every day I want to see how my
campers are doing on the table campers
are you ready for me to see your project
or do you want me to give you a second
are you ready all right so I'm gonna go
around the table and I'm gonna see how
how my campers did just so we kind of
get some ideas there so Keegan is up
first
so Keegan chose to use a spaceship and
now he's sailing around his island now
Keegan what he's done to make his island
possible she's made a spaceship a little
smaller that's a very clever thing to do
so there you lose let's go and see you
win one Keegan - I just go yeah he's got
a shortcut misty we're get his cutting
board on the outside get down there and
win Keegan final come on Devon if you
like to win one for me and come back by
them all right Bowen has a cool line and
now he's bones use lots of stats so go
ahead and play it though all right so
he's got a sleepy dragon that's coming
around oh he caught that tip that's a
dangerous tip you've got their bow I
consider that a feature but you can
always change things until you're happy
with
it's a dangerous game all right good job
see if you can win your game and then
we've got McKinley over here
McKinley Murray looks like it's Murray's
Island I got infected clear on there
sorry Michael it looks like she's got a
ship that's sailing around I mean right
now she's doing a speed of 10 it looks
great
so campers did you have fun with today's
exercise all right if you want more
here's what we've done in the past we
have encouraged people to try to build
one on their own from scratch that's the
same coding concepts but a different
theme so I'm not gonna work this with
you but see if if you if you would like
another thing to do see if you can make
a very similar game with a different
theme so here I'm doing a space-themed
right so I used a spaceship and I drew
planets and I chose to use a little
earth image that I that I found but it's
still the same thing if I touch one of
these colors Iraq and if I touch the the
green that's in the home I win I also
decorated this one with a little alien
men all right so that's all we've got
for today
we hope you had fun with it I think
today's was a great example I builds on
yesterday and it's gonna build for what
we do tomorrow and we'll see you next
time
[Music]